The only way you can change
the world is with stories.
And the bigger your legend becomes,
the easier it is to share the story.
People want to hear it.
They want to listen.
Winds to
35 knots or higher possible.
And thunderstorms.
Showers and thunderstorms.
We are in an environmental emergency.
And having this vessel out there
telling these stories is
actually a really hopeful and inspiring.
It looks like somebody just
dropped a fricking
chandelier right on the ocean.
Yeah.
You don't realize the size
and the scale of this oil rig.
It's a floating city.
Now we're on this mission to chase big oil
out of the Bahamas.
Just using our cameras.
All right, this is it.
Starboard bow.
This one is big and blue.
You can't miss it.
- It's huge.
- It's huge, yeah.
35 feet deep, 34 feet deep, 50, 48.
What's down there?
306, 48 to 306.
So I think we should explore right here.
It looks really great.
I don't worry about him.
He worries about me.
Got to worry about something.
Might as well be the love of my life.
I think we are going to spend
the rest of our lives
trying to save the ocean.
If anybody's uncomfortable,
they call the dive.
- We go up together.
- Okay.
It's so difficult to photograph
and film in the ocean.
Not many people can do it.
And until we cannot physically do it,
we're going to continue doing it.
National Geographic Magazine
is revealing its adventurers of the year.
They are chosen for
embodying the spirit of
adventure in groundbreaking ways.
Two of them did so as a couple,
Paul Nicklen and Cristina Mittermeier
are photographers.
They met in the cafeteria
of National Geographic's headquarters.
Their dramatic images
of the natural world have
won millions of social media followers,
turning them into conservation superstars.
While Paul specializes in wildlife
at the frozen ends of the earth,
Cristina captures the lives of
indigenous people all over the world.
In 2015,
the two marine biologists
cofounded SeaLegacy.
A non-profit organization
working to save our seas.
In the beginning
all we had was our Instagram account.
People really want to know
what it feels like to be a photographer.
What it feels like to be
sitting there in the stream
when a bear comes walking in.
I was cold. I was hungry.
I was scared. I was excited.
And so, we started posting those stories.
And it was like a scene out
of Forest Gump.
One day you look behind you
and there's thousands of people
following you.
Millions of people following you.
I really see the journey
we're going on is to be
a Jacques Cousteau 2.0
using modern technology.
Beating that drum constantly.
You can elicit an emotional
response from your followers.
You can make them care.
You can make them angry.
I just want them to feel it
and then from there,
decide what they want to do.
I think a lot of people have
already given up, you know?
Why care if everything is already doomed?
We still live in a beautiful planet.
There are still so many
amazing animals out there.
I want to be an ambassador for nature.
For all of us.
For my children for yours.
And so, making that connection
from here's a photograph to
here's how we begin a movement
of people who care.
A couple of nights of traveling, sailing,
living with Paul Nicklen.
Don't do it.
All right, this is where the makeup lives.
And all we need to do to
be presentable for Instagram
is use this mirror.
Oh God...
It's a disaster.
We're off to a place in the Bahamas
that has pristine waters,
rich abundance of wildlife,
great populations of sharks.
We're getting probably
anywhere from 10 to 20 emails
and texts a day saying,
"Help! We have a major issue."
Everywhere you look, you hear
screams of help for the environment.
This is nice. This is better.
These are all
these little simmering issues
that are going on in the world.
And SeaLegacy has become so big
that we can just now go into
and just throw gasoline on
these little simmering fires.
Our hope is to take this boat
around the world
and help tell the stories that
need to be told everywhere.
This is like the adventure of a lifetime.
And when we bought this boat
we basically didn't know
where to start.
And we could have thrown a dart
at a globe and landed anywhere,
but it is very difficult not
to fall in love with a place
like the Bahamas.
It's like candy.
It's gorgeous.
There's beautiful wildlife,
there's dolphins, there's sharks.
It's a stronghold for
many endangered species.
But now they have an opportunity
to drill for oil.
There's a shallow shoal
and there's a company called
the Stena IceMAX that
has applied for permit.
And we know what can happen
when big companies drill for oil.
And so, our story in
the Bahamas is this moment,
this crossroads.
You know, SeaLegacy is for the fish,
and we are for the whales
and for the dolphins.
So, our job in the Bahamas
is to remind people that this
is all still there.
But you have to protect it.
And if we can make that
happen here in the Bahamas,
then we can make it
happen elsewhere on the planet.
So, we have to succeed.
So, we know
where the IceMAX is based on
marine traffic,
'cause they've been at it
for almost two months.
My understanding is that
they only have 12 days left.
At some point, a dolphin is
going to wash up on a beach.
A whale is going to die from this.
Something is going to happen.
So, here's our plan.
First, we're going to photograph
the giant seagrass beds
that were just discovered.
Then we're going to sail
looking for big marine animals,
the whales, the sharks,
and finally, we're going to
make our way around
the northern tip of Andros
and sail through the night
to get to the oil rig under
the cover of darkness.
Great!
So A, we're going
to have the biggest body of work
ever created for the Bahamas
underwater and above
that showcase the beauty
of this place and to contrast that
we're going to have Goliath.
Yeah.
But first, let's get some epic,
beautiful footage.
When I'm shooting, I like to think
about myself like a membrane.
And on one side you have
the thing that I'm photographing,
and let it pass through that membrane,
people that will never
put their head underwater.
I want to be where that conversation goes
back and forth.
I love it, I just can't get enough of it.
I remember my dad coming home from work.
We were still living in Mexico City,
so my brother must have been eight or nine
and I was probably six or seven
and I was already fascinated by the ocean.
You know, I just loved it.
And he brought home a book and he had like
wrapped in newspaper.
He opened it up and it was
Jacques Cousteau, The Underwater World
and he gave it to Freddy.
And I was like, "Why to Freddy?"
You know, "I'm the one
who cares about this stuff."
To this day, I cannot fathom
that my dad never even saw it.
You know, that, that the gift was
lost on Freddy.
I would just sneak into
my brother's bedroom
after he got bored with it.
And you know, I would look,
I still have the book.
I think we do this to girls.
You know, we raised
them to believe that somehow
opportunities are better given to boys,
that some things are not for girls.
I grew up like that.
So many of my girlfriends,
equally interesting,
equally curious, they did nothing
but stay home and become housewives.
That was the expectation.
I remember my dad saying, you know,
"Who's going to want to marry you
if you go work on a fishing boat?"
Who's going to want to marry you?
Really?
I was able to redeem myself years later,
you know, I went to
University in Northern Mexico.
I wanted to be a marine biologist,
but the only thing they had
was fisheries biology.
That sounded close enough to me.
So, I graduated with
my dad in my ear saying,
"You know, biology, how are
you going to make a living?
It's not for girls."
And a friend of mine
had an uncle who owned
a hotel in Akumal.
And so I moved to the Yucatan
and I spent probably a year.
I mean, I had all the diving I wanted
because the hotel had a little dive shop.
So every day I would go
diving and then I would just
go in the jungle and chase the monkeys.
And towards the end of the year,
there was a hurricane.
Scientists came through the hotel
and they stayed there
and they offered me a job.
Conservation International.
And so I moved back to Mexico City
and I started working in conservation.
Can you imagine?
You know, I think
our goal is to do a wildlife
and nature biodiversity cross-section
of the entire Bahamas.
And one of the great announcements that,
I mean, this is secret, um,
hasn't been announced yet,
but the biggest seagrass beds
in the world,
underwater seagrass beds.
They are discovered here in
the Bahamas and they are by far
the largest in the world.
It's the biggest
scientific discovery
in the oceans in the last 10 years.
And it's on the banks here?
Right, right south of Nassau.
Yeah.
If you go to the Bahamas
you think of the beautiful ripples
of white on the sand, on the ocean floor,
the crystal blue clear water.
So, if I said to somebody.
"Wow, you should care about seagrass,"
they'd be like, "Yeah okay, whatever,
I'm tuned out already," right?
But if you can go down
underwater and connect
this whole ecosystem
from eagle rays and stingrays.
To following a shark through the seagrass
and she does this spiral move
to get rid of the remoras
that are attached to her,
you see all these species
that are connected to this environment.
And you realize how important it is.
And you use this beautiful
engaging mega-fauna to get
people to ultimately
fall in love with grass.
It's big and lush
and it really feels like
an underwater garden.
Seagrass is actually
the oldest living organism
on our planet.
CO2 carbon goes in.
Oxygen gets spit out.
Those are the lungs of the Bahamas.
So whenever someone says,
"Every second breath
you take comes from the sea."
That's what we're talking about.
I just don't think we appreciate
the importance of little things
like the roots of the seagrass.
Doesn't look like much,
but they might just be the solution.
You want the secret,
well, nature has been doing
it for four billion years.
You're going to put that
at risk so four or five guys
can get rich on oil.
From where we're trying to
head is where the Stena IceMAX
is down right here.
People are like,
"Well drilling's in the deep water."
Well so are the whales, you know.
People don't realize the power
of the most sophisticated
oil drilling at the biggest scale,
right in the middle
of a whale migratory corridor,
if there was an oil spill in that area.
Oh it would all go
and wash up in Florida.
That oil
would go right instantly into
the Gulf Stream
it would be along the entire
eastern seaboard of the United States.
Okay, pull on that sucker.
- Yeah.
A little more.
How are you?
I'm great! How are you?
I'm fine,
I'm looking out at the snow.
It's about 6 inches.
So, I'm looking at what
boots I'm gonna wear, and you?
Uh, yeah,
we're doing great.
Just wanted to check in
and just tell you we love you
and we think about you guys often and, uh,
find ourselves homesick, but...
Well, the same here.
Yeah, well, thank you for everything.
I love you very much.
And you look after yourselves, OK?
Call me. I like that
every once in a while.
It's so nice.
Yes, we will
for sure and give my love
to Aaron and Mark and, uh,
the puppies, of course.
And, and we'll talk to you soon, Mom.
- Will do.
- Okay.
OK, I love you. Take care.
Okay.
Love you too, okay bye-bye.
In 1972, when I was four years old,
my family moved to Baffin Island
because my dad got a job there.
It's a three-and-a-half-hour flight
on the big jet straight north.
We had moved into a community
of 190 Inuit people.
There are all these outpost camps,
your groceries came once a year by ship.
We didn't have a television.
We didn't have a radio.
We didn't even have a telephone.
Nobody had a telephone.
It was a strange place,
but I just got off on it.
And it was a very simple,
but very raw,
but very beautiful existence.
In our little town of Lake Harbour,
my mom had a little dark room.
She would take pictures,
she would process her negatives
in this bath.
And you would see these
beautiful moments of these
Inuit hunters just, you know,
people out on the land
and black and whites and us kids.
It's my only really sort of
sad moment in all of this is
that my mom had such a hardship
living in the North.
She saw so much troubling stuff
that when she came out of the Arctic,
she took her life's work.
All of her photography,
all of her slides...
She took this whole journey
we were on and just burned it.
She took gasoline and just burned it all.
And she wanted to
remove that chapter
from her life whereas I,
you know, I found myself
dreaming about the Arctic
and pursuing going back to the Arctic.
And being back with my Inuit friends.
I deeply fell in love with this place.
Let's do 10:00.
Definitely hear something down there.
Go to two.
Go nine.
I thought
it was just the microphone,
but it disappears it like...
Exactly, I think that static is
I think whales deep.
So it's working, which is the good news.
If those are whales,
they'd be then six, seven,
eight miles away.
I think we'll just go
another one-mile north.
Can I listen?
Mm-hmm.
Oh, wow. Amazing.
That noise
we're hearing is that way.
- ...or something.
- Okay.
- The danger distance.
- Yeah.
He likes the cold,
but he also likes the blue water.
Paul Nicklen is happiest
when he has a big animal that
he can just spend time with.
Okay, I'm launching the drone.
Shelton, I'm going to do a big arch to
port and come around.
Okay, yeah, I'm scoping the whole area.
I can't see them.
Shelton
is on top and he's got the drone
in the air.
Mishe is in the bow,
she's looking for fins.
And somehow I got stuck in the wheel,
but somebody has to drive, so.
Yeah,
you can see that really well.
Yeah, oh they're
surfaced, they're on the top.
They're
about 300 feet off the bow.
As best I can tell
it's just a pod of pilot whales.
180 honey, let's do it.
Last light of the day.
Turn off the engine, just
press the big black stop button.
Okay. We're stopped.
- Okay going in.
- Good luck!
I've always
been so in love with being
immersed in the ocean.
I'm with a wild animal.
I think it was second-year university,
one night I'm waiting
for a friend to go study
and I click on the TV for a second.
But here the water is clear
and the orcas linger near us.
It's these
two divers in the water.
And these orcas come up to them
and then swim around them.
And the orcas disappear into the depths.
Disappear into the haze below us,
as if departing.
Then they come back up
each with a shark in their mouths.
She parades before us like
a cat proudly displaying a mouse.
And they circle around
Jacques Cousteau and his team,
and then disappear.
And I was just like,
"That's what I'm going to
do for the rest of my life.
I know exactly what I'm going to do.
That's it."
From that minute on, I was obsessed.
I was all in.
I was failing almost every class.
And I, I just basically lived underwater.
I just took down my camera
and I shot and I shot and I shot
three to four times a day, every day
and my bedroom was
full with wet dive gear.
And it was just foul.
But I didn't care.
Because I was just dove,
dove every second I could.
I remember I went home.
My neighbor was a photographer
and he's like,
"Let's do a slideshow at my house."
I was so proud, you know,
and I put these pictures up on
the wall and, and my dad said,
"I think this is an absolute waste
of time and money.
Why would you waste your
time doing this?" You know?
And I was just like, "Ugh."
The hardest part was emotionally.
I think everybody telling me,
including my parents,
my friends, my coworkers,
"You are going to fail."
And so I was mad at the world
for telling me that
I couldn't do this.
So I packed up my gear
and I went to a pilot and I said,
"I need you to drop me off
as far away from civilization as you can."
And I said, "If I'm alive in four months,
I will be at the Arctic Ocean.
I'm just going to live
out here alone with animals."
Took 300 rolls of film.
And I remember standing
on the Barren Lands after
probably a week of being there.
I was lonely. I kind of wanted to go home.
Like, "What the hell am I doing?"
And, "Everybody's right, I am a failure."
And I remember just screaming one day
until my lungs were just raw.
And it was after that,
that I sort of just settled in.
And I went from that,
to being almost panicked that
this trip wasn't long enough.
I only had three months left,
and I had to make
every second count.
And, you know, I lost 50 pounds.
I kind of became like a wild animal.
You know, I could see forever,
like your senses become so in tune that
it became like this drug to
be out there in, in nature.
And when the trip was wrapping up,
I was just horrified,
sad that it had to end, you know?
My now ex-wife came in
for the last two weeks of the trip and,
you know, it was, uh,
I remember being very frustrated
with her that she couldn't see,
like, I'm like,
"The muskoxen are right
there in front of you."
And they were like
probably seven miles away.
She kept saying, "I can't see them."
That was kind of my,
my transition into the next chapter
of life.
Just to use all that I had
learned from the Inuit
and my survival skills and to
just think about life, what was next.
He's a very good outdoorsman.
He's a very good survivalist.
And that allows him to do something that
a lot of photographers can't do.
And that is showing us intimate nature.
So for him, it's not
enough to have a telephoto lens
and be 200 feet away.
He has to be this close.
I've never been
naive enough to think
that I have special relationship
with animals.
But I do believe there's a wildness to me
from spending so much time with them
that I give off an energy
and a vibe around them.
That they can work with it.
And so
when you look at his photographs
you feel like you are in the photograph
with the animal.
I've had thousand-pound bears
sleep against my tripod,
which is also touching my leg.
Wild leopard seals come
up within two feet of me.
So that's
what makes Paul Nicklen
one of the greatest
photographers of our generation.
He's shown us nature in a different way.
That is intimate and really present.
Mama and a little baby.
Amazing.
Oh my God, look at it!
And then the next
dive is even closer and sharper.
So, it was a good pass.
- Those look great.
Yeah?
Mom and a baby.
It's dreamy, right?
Very beautiful.
Dreamy backlight feel to it.
Nice! That's the reflection on top--
- Yeah.
- It's gorgeous.
There's an Inuit expression
that Paul taught me.
They say, "Tusu," which means
I am happy for what you have
but I want it for myself too.
So I have Tusu.
I think I had a lot of practice
finding my space next to someone
like Paul, because I was married
for 20 years
to Russ Mittermeier,
larger than life, adventurer,
explorer and scientist.
And the President of
Conservation International.
I had my first child when I was 23.
I was a very young mom.
You know, my grandmother
wanted me to have a baby.
I felt like this pressure, you know,
that it was time to have children.
Russ and I lived in Great Falls, Virginia,
which is an affluent
community near Washington DC.
So I, I started a little business.
Cristina Mittermeier Photography.
And so they wanted me to take
their picture for the holidays.
So I had them like on a rotation.
You know, I had this little spot
in front of the waterfalls.
And I had like three bookings
every afternoon.
So I had this little
business going making portraits.
At the same time, I was
going on these amazing trips
to the Amazon and to Papua New Guinea
with Russ and taking pictures.
He would go off at 5:00 in the morning
to chase monkeys.
And I had to stay
in these villages with the kids.
And having kids in remote communities,
it's like a magic door opener.
You know, people will
come out of their homes
and they just wanted to
touch these kid, you know,
and they would grab her
and before you know it,
you're in the middle of the family.
And I was like, "Holy!"
I had access to people's
very intimate spaces in life
and I could take pictures.
It was awesome.
And I was like, "Okay, game on."
You know?
We're sitting here on the northern Amazon,
waiting for some Indians coming to, uh,
do a welcoming dance for us.
So the funny thing is they came,
they went right by and they said,
"Oh, we'll come back. We'll come back."
So we're sitting here waiting for them.
She always surprises me.
There's always something
there that is just different
and beautiful and fresh.
Like what I can do with animals,
where I'm relaxed with them
and things happen for me with wildlife,
she's like that with people.
I've spoken
to women photographers
who think that being a woman
is a disadvantage.
For me, it was like a superpower,
you know?
You are just non-threatening, you know,
people don't care that you have a camera.
You're a woman.
And I realized, you know, if I focus on
this aspect of humans and nature,
maybe there's something
that not many people are doing.
And I think that's a very big difference
between male and female photographers, uh.
For me, it's about the relationships,
you know,
the photographs I want to make are about
the mother and the baby or the, you know,
the connection.
For a lot of the men,
it's about the action.
The bear, the shark!
Directly off the stern.
Right here off the stern, he just came up.
Wild tiger.
I didn't think we're going to see one.
Amazing.
Hey you guys hang on,
he's circling a stingray.
- Is he?
- Yeah.
- Are you kidding me?
- No, no.
- Whereabouts?
- Right under the drone.
That's pretty awesome.
Straight ahead.
Yep, right out in front of you.
Right towards those people.
Right here!
Swim this way! Circling back to you!
Where's the shark?
Right behind you guys.
On the far side of us.
10 feet, 15 feet.
That ray's tail's
been cut off.
Oh!
But he's about five feet long.
Do you
think that stingray is dying?
Yeah, I saw his eyes,
but they're just fully
covered over it, like fungus.
- Yeah.
- So that's why he can't see him.
And he, he
just moved 180, but very,
very slow and sluggish
and I just think it's a small shark.
I think it's terrified.
- Yeah.
- I mean, he's scared of me.
He's scared of this ray.
I mean, he's just cautious, right?
And we see tiger sharks
as these vicious beasts.
And yet they're patiently
waiting for a stingray that has
no barb to die rather than
risk getting hurt, you know.
Can you imagine that stingray?
Coming to this crossroads in time.
It's just, it's just very powerful.
It's, it's very fortunate.
It's sad. It's beautiful.
It's all of it, you know?
It's kind of how I want to go.
I've been always sort of
fascinated how I'm going to die.
I just don't want to die in a car
and I want my death to be cool.
I remember I was very close
to getting killed
by an 8,000-pound breeding elephant seal.
I didn't realize he'd been breeding
all day
and he was hot and he was in the water,
cooling off the water was four feet deep.
And I swam up to him to take
his picture and he turned on me
and here's an animal
that's when he rears up,
he's 11 feet tall in the air, you know,
and he's rearing up
and trying to crush me.
I'm the only defense I have.
Every time he tried to
bite me and his teeth are,
you know, four inches long.
I would just shove my housing
in his mouth and just push off
and I'm alone, you know.
And it was kind of calming.
I'm like, "So, this is
how I'm going to die."
I remember having that thought like,
"Oh, so this is it."
And, but finally, I took my,
my snorkel out of my mouth,
and I went, "Sean!" I yell,
put it back in my mouth.
Boom! And he just kept coming
after me, coming after me.
And finally, I crawled out in the beach,
but I, you know, my arms were
just swollen from the impact.
I think he has a very different
threshold for fear than I do,
so he is able to tolerate
a lot more risk than I can.
I just like
those raw moments where animals
are in control, I just feel very alive
when I'm vulnerable
and uncomfortable and a bit scared.
It was the first weekend in the Bahamas,
I was having quite a bit of regret,
I'm like, "I've just walked
away from the Arctic where
I do get to feel vulnerable
from the rawness of walrus
and ice diving and leopard seals."
And I was starting to question myself,
"I'm doing coral, in crystal blue water.
Like this is too easy.
I don't feel scared."
And then just as I was
having those thoughts,
we found the bottlenose dolphins.
And I jumped in the water
with one dolphin.
And then to witness
seven dolphins all diving deep
into the sand and it looks like
you're flying over the moon
with all the craters,
it's called crater feeding.
And it became one of the most beautiful,
poetic moments of, of my career.
And the tagline came up to me
that this is the only drilling that
should be taking place in the Bahamas.
So what's our plan when we get
to the oil drilling?
I was saying that
when we get to the Stena IceMAX,
they're not going to let us hang out.
I don't think
they're going to invite us
on board for coffee, but I think that...
Oh,
I think they will unleash,
unleash their security boats on us.
So I think we have one chance and that is
pretending to be
a sailing cruising vessel,
film from the deck.
And as we pass, as we leave,
fly the drone before they come
and put the run on us.
They can't legally put
the run on us though.
Oh, they can
and they are protected
by the Bahamian government and--
No like we're not
going to be 50 feet from them.
We'll be half a mile from them.
Okay, just know that we risk getting
kicked out of the country
for harassing boat.
We're not harassing.
Just cruising by.
I'll leave it with you,
but I wouldn't hang out
because those ships,
you know, they are under threat of piracy
and terrorism and stuff.
You know, we very seldom fight.
I wish we had a more
healthy fighting life.
We don't fight, but we disagree.
So, then...
Going back to that
moment when you met Paul.
You were in the room for the first time.
What had brought you into that room?
So I was going to these
nature photography conferences.
Russ would keep the kids
and I would travel
to meet other photographers.
It was so intimidating.
'Cause they all had their portfolios
and these big binders.
And I had nothing.
I had 10 pictures of indigenous people
that nobody wanted to see.
So I was nobody, but I would raise my hand
and I would say, you know,
"Could we, you know,
perhaps think about contributing
more of our work to
environmental organizations?"
And I was basically told to
shut up and sit down, like,
"Yeah, we don't do
environment here little lady."
A lot of photographers had
a really hard time connecting
the dots between their work
and the conservation outcome.
I was trying to tell that story for them.
I was living
in White Horse, Yukon.
A friend of mine came over and he goes,
"There's this big organization
being launched, the ILCP,
the International League of
Conservation Photographers.
And, and this woman
named Christina Mittermeier is
launching it in Alaska.
And I'm going, I've been invited."
And I'm like, "Wow."
And I became sort
of instantly jealous and...
So I hadn't me her yet.
And then it was probably six,
seven months later, I was back
at National Geographic for meetings.
And, um, there was Cristina Mittermeier.
We were
in one of those meetings that
National Geographic
does for their photographers
and it was my first meeting.
She looked beautiful.
She's in this sort of Mexican,
the bracelets and the long skirt
and that very Mexican flair.
And there she is, looks just like, to me,
Catherine Zeta-Jones.
And there was an empty chair next to me.
And Paul walked in,
all Canadian.
He was wearing plaid and corduroys
and he was really cute.
And I was so nervous.
And she goes,
"Hello I'm Cristina Mittermeier.
I want you to sit next
to me and flirt with me."
Those are the first
words out of her mouth.
I've learned that she says
crazy things when she's nervous,
so she was nervous to meet me.
I was nervous to meet her.
By that time I knew that Russ and
I were not going to make it.
You know, it's one of those
where after you've been married
for about 15 years,
you start making a plan.
I was like, "You know what,
I'm still young.
I, I don't want to be here
10 years from now,
still feeling this way."
And Paul was on assignment in Mexico.
And I remember I was driving my kids
and I'm on my cell phone.
And, "Paul, Paul!" You know, I said,
"I need some of your pictures
for this press release."
And he said, "Talk to my agent."
And she's like, "Yeah,
Paul's going to need to be
paid for these."
Oh my God.
I was like, how can you call yourself
a conservation photographer
and you cannot even, you know,
allow the use of your images
for press release?
I was pissed. I was furious.
So I think in order to make it up to me,
he said that he would come
on an expedition,
we were documenting the Yucatan Peninsula
and just how quickly it's changed.
And so I put together a team
of 20 photographers.
I said, "I'll be Paul's assistant.
I'll pick him up from the airport."
And of all the photographers,
he was the most difficult
to work with because I knew
he didn't want to be there.
We ended up shooting together for a week
and diving in these
beautiful cenotes in Mexico.
There is something
really interesting that happens
when you dive with the same person.
And it is like a choreography,
it is like a dance.
When I was married to Russ Mittermeier,
he was so afraid of letting me dive
that I didn't dive almost in 20 years.
And so when I met Paul
and I started diving with him,
it was just like the most romantic,
amazing thing.
To have this dive partner
who loves to be underwater
as much as you do.
And we were staying
in a little house that we had rented
and I was like, "Oh my God, this is like,
we're in a honeymoon."
Hello, hello,
check, check one, two, three,
Cristina cooking Mexican tonight.
Happy birthday, to me.
Happy Birthday.
Happy birthday to you
Cha, cha, cha.
Happy birthday to Christina
- I love you.
- Aww.
And many more.
I love you too.
And after we fell in love and, you know,
started working together,
I was his assistant in the field
and I was his fixer.
- Okay, one more.
- I'm very uncomfortable.
No, don't be uncomfortable,
get used to it.
He was
the photographer on assignment,
but I was traveling with him
and helping him with everything.
I'm gonna take your picture.
So we did probably 10 assignments for
NatGeo that way.
Just a dream
person to be out there with,
always happy and...
Just you know, I went from
loving working with her
to needing her in my life all the time.
And we went off on this journey together.
Paul was the first person to really
look at me and say, "Okay
you want to be a photographer."
Like until then I was fighting for it.
And he's like, "No, no,
you are photographer
and you're really good to."
It's amazing
when somebody says that to you.
So I brought her with me out on
a National Geographic assignment
and as I was standing there on
the shores, these two
photographers took me aside,
and they said, "We see
you're close to Cristina
like your friends," I'm like, "Yeah,"
and they said,
"We need you to go tell her that
she is not a photographer.
She is here in service to us."
That pissed me off.
I mean, there's like this
contract between a photographer
and an assistant.
You're not there to shoot.
You're there to facilitate his story.
No, I triggered some people, you know,
I trigger a certain kind of man,
a man who then has to
scold me or school me,
or tell me what's what.
They're all trying to bring her down
because photographers are like
a bunch of hungry wolves,
and I think being a Mexican woman living
in the United States,
she got a lot of that, you know?
Oh, yes.
Cristina, you're
the best president-elect I know.
Uh, uh...
I, I, I don't expect a recount.
I was just
so in awe of her determination
and power and perseverance
and her leadership,
and photographers were following her.
And my marriage had sort
of been over for many years.
It became just more of a decision,
I'm going to go do conservation, you know,
with this other woman
who's on fire, you know.
And we're going to go
fight for this planet.
That's all we're going to
do for the next 30 years.
I think
the biggest gift that Paul has
given me, he's been that confidence that,
that I do know what I'm doing
and I, maybe I am good at it.
Yesterday
you were an amazing Captain.
I captained it.
You did; you're captain.
Antarctica was a transformative
experience because for 10 years
I had been Paul's assistant and fixer.
And for Antarctica specifically,
Paul insisted that I be a photographer
on the expedition.
And I never wanted to be
a National Geographic photographer.
My ambition is to do conservation,
but it was like, "Wow, you know,
what a, an amazing privilege
and honor to be asked."
I was the only woman on the expedition
and I was kind of
half expecting for the men
to mansplain things to me
and tell me how to do things.
But they didn't, they were amazing.
They were like, "Okay Christina,
you're on splits, you're going
to be in the water all day.
See you at dinner."
You know? And I was like,
"Okay, I'm on my own."
It's fantastic.
You've got all these chicks.
These Chinstraps, Gentoos, Adlies.
They're all going to
sea right now, and, uh,
the leopard seals are here
to pick them off.
And they feed all morning
and then they rest all day.
I don't feel threatened
or scared in the company of animals.
So I have a very calm demeanor.
And I think that really helps.
And I spent about an hour
and a half first with one and then
with two, and at some point there were
five leopard seals around me,
wonderfully curious, photogenic,
super interesting animals.
And I was trying to
make a split photograph of
a leopard seal and an iceberg.
Guys, Peter. Good.
We need to
think about getting people out.
They're getting a little aggro.
Keith, time.
They come out of nowhere.
That's why I'm
yelling, "Incoming, incoming!"
Oh! It's like a ghost.
So beautiful.
Whoo!
- Yeah baby.
- Yeah baby!
- Well done guys.
Thanks, buddy.
Thank you.
That was awesome. That was unbelievable.
Life-changing really.
Hey you big girl.
You're beautiful.
So yesterday I was trying
to photograph this little
lonely penguin on the iceberg,
and as I was shooting there,
you know, all of a sudden
I saw one leopard seal come by
and then two leopard seals come by.
And pretty soon there were four or five.
So I want to try to do that again because
they were catching penguins right there.
You know, I got
a little concerned yesterday or
when I heard you were
in the water alone with
five leopard seals.
'Cause they are amazing animals.
They're like big dogs.
They're super cool.
There are a lot of fun.
They're the probably the most
beautiful animal you'll ever
watch underwater,
but five of them together.
I mean, they are,
they're nature's coolest killing machines.
I mean, they, one wants to mess with you.
Just, you know, be just be careful.
They, they seem to be pretty happy
eating penguins like popcorn.
Yeah.
There's a lot of food for them,
but still, it's not a given
that it's all going to go 100%.
I have almost lost Christina on
a dive once and it was a very,
it was just an awful
feeling like sickening.
And, um, you know,
so I, I think that my
safety barometer of that
gray line there, you push your limits of,
of what's right and wrong,
what's safe and not safe.
That line has come way down for me.
'Cause I look it through,
like, if I'm dead, I'm dead.
If I lose Christina,
then you have to live with that.
I'm always keeping an eye on her,
I never wanted to be sort of
patronizing or too protective of her,
but I'm very protective of her.
But, you know, who am I to say,
"I do this and you can't,"
you know, we're equal out there.
I'm very happy
that I was able to do that story.
Forevermore, I will be able to say that
I'm a contributing photographer
to National Geographic,
and that is a huge deal to me.
I now know that I am at the top
of my game and that I have what
it takes to produce the kinds
of stories that move people.
And I am happy that I get
to create this content now
for SeaLegacy and for this
conservation work that
I'm going to do until I die.
Now we're
going to get into some of
the nitty-gritty conservation work.
My understanding is we're 115 miles away
from the IceMAX, right
where they're drilling.
So are we going to come in
direct at the ship sort of hard
and fast, or are we going
to come in timid and shy from
the distance and get
some drones in the air?
We could be there
by 6:00 a.m. tomorrow morning.
We can come in just under
the cover of darkness
tomorrow morning, even though
they legally can't ram us
or chase us out of there, they're
going to do everything they can
to get us out of there.
And then from there, our excuse,
"Oh, we're a Canadian boat, eh?
No like we're out here fishing.
And, um, we saw you have
a really cool boat and, um,
what are your distance restrictions?"
And they're going to be
like, "One mile," you know,
and you're like, "Okay, thank you.
We'll make sure we,
we follow those rules."
And we'll sit at a mile.
When you're starting out your
career you measure success
and it's nice to win a BBC Award
or a World Press Photo Award.
But after a while, you're like,
"Okay, I know how to tell a story."
And now we measure
success in having our own wins.
Whether it's taking on big oil in Norway,
I was in Moscow last year
and just like being glared down
by the entire oil industry from Norway.
If you've ever been to
a place called Lofoten,
it is truly one of the most
beautiful places in the world
where every year 1200 orcas
show up to feed on the herring.
You get humpback whales and fin whales.
We need to protect a lot of
these critical key habitats
on our earth if we want to continue
having life the way it is. Thank you.
They're staring at me while I'm on stage.
And Putin had just given an address
and just hating me because we had won.
We chased them out of these
grounds in the Lofoten region,
just using our cameras.
We had helped a group shut down
the entire drift net fishery
off the coast of California,
that has a nine-to-one bycatch
because we went diving
and showed how gross it is.
Tragically, last night, we found
a humpback whale wrapped
up in this big, heavy crab pot line.
We were able to get a lot of it free,
but it still has a lot on it.
It's still out there
fighting for its life.
We partner with these organizations
like this tiny nonprofit in Canada,
they literally are three people.
But they figured out a great idea.
They said, "If we don't
want people to hunt wolves,
all we have to do is
buy the hunting tenure."
You know, we just
rallied our followers we said,
"This is what we want to do
and this is how much we need,"
and sure enough,
within days we had the money.
And not ever again a single
wolf will be killed there.
My dream is that
anybody sees SeaLegacy coming,
not just the boat, but the organization.
And they're just going to roll over.
'Cause they just can't handle
300 million eyes, you know,
something three times bigger
than eyes on the Super Bowl,
all of a sudden focused on them
and what they're doing,
that, that excites me.
We have
been sailing through the night.
And we are now 7.7 nautical miles
away from the Stena Ice.
We can see them in our radar
and they probably can
see us in their radar.
And they are probably wondering
what we are doing here.
And so we need to come up with
an answer fairly, fairly pronto.
Okay, coming down.
Are you guys
ready for me to go into the wind?
Yeah, standby,
all right all sails down.
Okay.
It looks like somebody just dropped
a frickin' chandelier right on the ocean.
- It's a city.
It's a city, yeah.
It's a floating city.
And the one thing that I don't want is
to get kicked out of the Bahamas.
To get reported to
the Bahamian authorities.
I don't think we admit to journalists.
We're just in transit, um.
Looks like our C-O-G is, you know,
two miles, that, is
that an acceptable distance?
Are we close to, uh,
I want to change our course
here pretty quick.
So we are trying to already debate,
we obviously don't already have
our plan completely together
'cause Cristina now thinks we should issue
that we are journalists.
And telling here to photograph the ship.
I think that that's not smart.
Um...
Then they're going to get
really obviously suspicious.
I'm going to alter course as
if we're going to miss them.
I mean,
imagine the radio call going
right now to the Bahamian Coast Guard.
I, I think lying is not the best policy.
I think it's just better to tell the truth
and see what they say.
Do you really think you can get
a great shot with a drone?
You think two miles is, can get you there?
What's, what's two miles in meters?
- Three kilometers.
- Like three kilometers?
3.2 kilometers.
So it's like two is the, is as far,
especially in like with
a bit of wind like this,
you get there and have like
10 minutes to shoot that, man.
My goal is that we have this,
this angle 2.4 miles,
and by then we're going to be
in radio contact.
Too dark.
SeaLegacy One.
- Paul you want to take that?
- Wait, wait, wait, wait, wait...
This is Stena Icemax.
IceMAX,
IceMAX, yes, this is
the SeaLegacy One, go ahead.
So, for information,
we are a drilling rig.
Our operations are
the only operations in this area.
And we request a wide berth of at least
two nautical miles.
Yeah,
okay, Roger, copy that.
We are, uh, just dealing with some sails,
and then we are going to
head to Cay Sal Bank, um.
And then, um, but we will,
we will maintain two nautical miles,
we will give you a wide berth, um.
And if there's, uh,
come back to us 1, we'll stay on 1-6.
Yeah, okay Captain,
thank you very much. I appreciate that.
Yeah.
Yeah, okay, copy.
Thank you.
- Two miles.
- We got our number.
- Okay.
- So that means 1.8.
That's the number we wanted.
Perfect.
All right, this is it.
You can barely see it behind me.
Right above my head.
There is this Stena IceMAX.
It's a, an oil drilling ship
here in the southern waters
of the Bahama.
My hope is that there's no oil
and that they just
give up and go home.
But if they do find oil,
then we have to create a case
for a better alternative.
Building a blue economy,
a future that's more sustainable
for Bahamians and for the world.
I love the irony
that they have a polar bear
with ice written on their ship.
And this is the one thing
that's ultimately destroying
the habitat of polar bears.
You know, there's not much else we can do.
We've already been issued
a two-mile alert by these guys.
If we want to fly back and we want
to keep working in the Bahamas,
I think we're going to have to be
respectful of that, unfortunately.
So good.
Wow, that is nice Shelton.
- Well done.
- Gotta do like a...
- It's kind of nice.
- Yeah.
That shot right
there to me it says it all.
It's actually in
many ways, it's the scariest.
Yeah.
This beautiful blue ocean, you know,
look at the slick coming off the boat.
Is that oil or is that sand or sediment?
What is it?
It's pretty shocking
that something that big
is here, drilling.
It's good.
Very good, very proud.
Everybody is going to love this.
So good.
Something that I always
find so impressive is just
Paul's ability to execute
on expeditions, you know,
to kind of visualize what
we need to do, plan for it.
And then just put us in
the place where we need to be.
I think 99% of our success is just
Paul's experience with expeditions.
I think of
like as tight as incriminating
as possible without being illegal,
you know.
That's powerful right there.
Pull that,
pull that, pull that.
That's nice.
It's something like that,
where you look at the eyes.
Okay.
So I just received an email
from the president of BREEF, which is
one of the leading non-profits
here in the Bahamas.
They have been spearheading the effort
to get, uh, oil drilling out of here.
Whilst they will encounter oil,
commercial volumes of oils have
not been proven at this well location.
Drilling has now ceased
and the well will now
be permanently plugged and abandoned.
And we need to push now
for permanent protections
from oil drilling in the future.
This will send a message
to the world that we take
the protection
of our environment seriously,
that we care about the current and future
well-being of our people.
And that we are serious
about building a climate-resilient future
and I think the country is celebrating.
Yes! Yes! Yes!
You never know
how these campaigns are going to go.
You know, maybe we all get
to be heroes in this case,
but we're going to keep
gathering the assets that
allow us to keep that narrative on, uh,
going in case they do
rear their heads again.
300,000 views in two hours.
We're going to hit a million views
and probably 10,000 comments,
which will be one of our more
successful engagement posts
in a long time on something
that's really important.
So people can sign petitions
and put their name and voice to it.
And I think on a, on a bigger thing,
you know, it keeps
feeding people with hope.
Change is possible.
Change is happening.
Incredible, this is
what I need when I do splits.
When you what?
When I
do splits, this the kind of sky.
It's all about the empty spaces
I learned once in a Sony video,
that's where the magic
lives it's in the empty spaces.
Are you making fun of me?
But photographing four million years
of evolutionary perfection.
That's...
- It is very pretty.
- It is quite lovely.
I've always been in awe of her
and definitely in love with her
since the first time I met her, you know,
when she said, "Come and sit next to me."
Now she is one of the great
female photographers in the world.
And I'm excited to see
what happens with her next.
This is a great scene!
I, I want to make stuff
that really transcends.
Something bigger than itself.
You know, compelling and poignant.
It's the work that I am going to do
because I have to,
'cause how can I not?
On my deathbed,
I just want to know that
we saved a lot of habitat
and a lot of species.
The more I go on this
journey with Cristina,
and the more we have
the work with SeaLegacy,
the more responsibility
I feel to tell stories.
When you have the cameras,
you get to control how the story ends.
I think being out in the water
and being a beacon of hope, of inspiration
I think is really important.
I don't want to move to Mars.
I have no desire to go live
in a frickin' glass bubble.
We are living in heaven,
to think that there's been
four billion years of
evolution to arrive at this
moment of perfection where
you know, this place is just beautiful.
Where we can swim in crystal-clean water
and you're surrounded by
grizzly bears and black bears
and there's whales that come up to you.
And it's here and now.
We're just lucky we get to do this.
We really are.
This is, you don't retire from this.
You know, you're with this
until, until you sign off.
Until, you win or die, yeah.
Captioned by
Cotter Media Group.