The only way you can change
the world is with stories.
And the bigger your legend becomes,
the easier it is to share the story.
People want to hear it.
They want to listen.
Winds to
35 knots or higher possible.
And thunderstorms.
Showers and thunderstorms.
We are in an environmental emergency.
And having this vessel out there
telling these stories is
actually a really hopeful and inspiring.
It looks like somebody just
dropped a fricking
chandelier right on the ocean.
Yeah.
You don't realize the size
and the scale of this oil rig.
It's a floating city.
Now we're on this mission to chase big oil
out of the Bahamas.
Just using our cameras.
All right, this is it.